Guide to the Rudolph Dunbar Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Rudolph Dunbar Papers
1938-1986
JWJ MSS 174
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.50
(10 boxes)
The Rudolph Dunbar Papers document the professional activities of clarinetist, conductor, music critic, teacher and journalist Rudolph Dunbar. Series in this collection include Correspondence, Professional Papers, Photographs and Other Papers. Among those represented in the correspondence series include Coretta Scott King, Eslanda Robeson, and British parliament member Robert Allan. Professional papers include press releases, German propaganda of African Americans during World War II, and music programs from Dunbar's performancesas a music conductor. Photographs of independence day celebrations of former British colonies in Africa and the Caribbean make up a large portion of the photographs alongside highlights of Dunbar's music career as a conductor and teacher. Photographs also include dignitaries and celebrities of the day such as Kwame Nkrumah, Queen Elizabeth II, Prince Phillip and Jesse Owens.
Dunbar, Rudolph, 1938-1986
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Rudolph Dunbar, 1974-1986.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1938-1977 II. Professional Papers, 1944-1984 III. Photographs, 1940-1975 IV. Other Papers, 1963-1986.
Biographical / Historical
Rudolph Dunbar was born on April 5, 1899 in Nabacalis, British Guiana (now known as Guyana). Dunbar's birthdate is uncertain as he gave various dates throughout his career. However, records show that his actual birthdate is April 5, 1899 according to the Danish Immigration Office file V. 76420 of March 1929, and various ship passenger lists. Dunbar held many positions throughout his life including clarinetist, music critic, orchestra conductor, music teacher and journalist. Dunbar began his musical career as a clarinetist in 1912 while in the British Guiana Militia band. He later moved to the United States in 1919 to study music composition, piano, and clarinet playing at the Institute of Musical Art (Now the Julliard School). After graduation, Dunbar continued his musical education in France, Germany, and Austria. He studied music composition with Paul Vidal, clarinet playing with Louis Cahuzac as well as conducting with Phillip Gaubert and Felix Weingartner. In 1931, Dunbar created the Rudolph Dunbar School of Clarinet Playing in London, England. In 1942, he became the first musician of African descent to conduct the London Philharmonic Orchestra at the noted Royal Albert Hall in London, England. Other noted orchestras Dunbar conducted include the Liverpool Philharmonic Orchestra, and the Berliner Philharmoniker Orchestra. Dunbar was also the London correspondent for the Associated Negro Press and reported information of Great Britain during World War II. A journalist throughout his life, he also documented the independence of several African and Caribbean countries from British colonial rule. Dunbar continued his career as a musician and journalist until his death in London, England on June 10, 1988.
Scope and Contents
The Rudolph Dunbar Papers document the professional activities of clarinetist, conductor, music critic, teacher and journalist Rudolph Dunbar. Series in this collection include Correspondence, Professional Papers, Photographs and Other Papers. Among those represented in the correspondence series include Coretta Scott King, Eslanda Robeson, and British parliament member Robert Allan. Professional papers include press releases, German propaganda of African Americans during World War II, and music programs from Dunbar's performancesas a music conductor. Photographs of independence day celebrations of former British colonies in Africa and the Caribbean make up a large portion of the photographs alongside highlights of Dunbar's music career as a conductor and teacher. Photographs also include dignitaries and celebrities of the day such as Kwame Nkrumah, Queen Elizabeth II, Prince Phillip and Jesse Owens.
Conductors (Music) -- Great Britain; Journalists -- Great Britain; Clarinetists -- Great Britain; Photojournalism -- Africa; Photojournalism -- West Indies; Photographs; Conductors (Music) -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Journalists -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Allan, Robert, 1914-1979; Dunbar, Rudolph, 1938-1986; Elizabeth, Queen of Great Britain, II, 1926- -- Portraits; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006; Nkrumah, Kwame, 1909-1972 -- Portraits; Owens, Jesse, 1913-1980; Philip, Prince, consort of Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1921- -- Portraits; Robeson, Eslanda Goode, 1896-1965; Associated Negro Press
- Correspondence, 1938–1977; Series I
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged alphabetically by last name.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the professional correspondence of Rudolph Dunbar. Letters regarding Dunbar's music performances such as those at the Royal Albert Hall and the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra are in this series. Many letters from British parliment member Robert Allan also document Dunbar's trials in securing steady work as a music conductor in a field that included few people of African descent.
  - "A" general, 1951–1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allan, Robert, 1955–1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "B" general, 1942–1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bacewicz, Grazyna, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barnet, Claude, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - British Broadcasting Company (BBC), 1959–1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brockway, Fenner, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "C" general, 1942–1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Coleridge, Taylor Jessie F., 1942–1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Coleridge, Taylor Avril, 1943-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - "D" general, 1942–1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Driberg, Tom, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "E" general, 1942–1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "F" general, 1939–1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "G" general, 1941–1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gallup, Donald, 1975–1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Green, William, 1966–1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "H" general, 1942–1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "J" general, 1942–1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "K" general, 1941–1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - King, Coretta Scott, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "L" general, 1942–1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "M" general, 1941–1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "O" general, 1942–1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - O'Brian, E.D., 1968–1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "P" general, 1941–1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "R" general, 1938–1953 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Robeson, Eslanda Goode, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "S" general, 1939–1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Schuyler, Josephine, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Still, Grant William, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29a)
  - "T" general, 1945–1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "V" general, 1942–1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "W" general, 1942–1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Young, P. B., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Invitations, Circa 1947–1975 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Unidentified, 1942–1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Professional Papers, 1944–1984; Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains materials that document Rudolph Dunbar's music and journalism career. Items such as his personal press passes, press releases and music programs are in this series. Also included from Dunbar's work as a news correspondent during World War II are excerpts of Nazi German war propaganda against African Americans. Journals detailing the schedule of British ceremonial state visits to African countries such as Kenya, Nigeria, Tanzania and Zaire are also contained within this series.
  - Affidavit, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Ceremonial state visit to Kenya, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ceremonial state visit to Nigeria, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Ceremonial state visit to Tanzania, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Ceremonial state visit to Zaire, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - News clippings, 1947–1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - German war propaganda, 1942–1943 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Martin Sullivan's address for the late Martin Luther King Jr., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Memorial service for Martin Luther King, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Norman Washington Manley Memorial Service Program, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Orrett Rhoden piano recital, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Periodical New England, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - President of Nigeria State Visit to the United Kingdom, 1981-1981 (Box 9, Folder 48a-48c)
    Ephemera from the former Nigerian President Alhaji Shehu Shagari's visit to the United Kingdom in 1981. A transcript of a speech given by President Alhaji Shehu Shagari is also included.
  - Press passes, 1944–1973 (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
  - Press releases, 1967–1975 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Programs related to Rudolph Dunbar, 1939–1977 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Proms 84 press release, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Sir Alexander Bustmante memorial service program, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Ten Jamaican Sculptors, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1938–1983; Series III
  This series contains photographs, scrapbooks and news clippings that document Rudolph Dunbar's career as a journalist, music conductor, teacher and critic. Photographs include independence day celebration of African and Caribbean countries from British colonial rule. Dignitaries depicted within this series include former Ghanaian president Kwame Nkrumah, Queen Elizabeth II Prince Phillip of England and Jesse Owens.
  - Ghana independence celebration, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Indepence celebrations of former British colonies, 1947–1973 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Music and journalism career, Circa 1938-1986 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Photo album, Circa 1940-1975 (Box 4)
  - Various Portraits, Circa 1938-1986 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Clippings by and about Dunbar, 1934–1972 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 64)
  - Articles, 1967–1983 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Scrapbook Volume I, 1938-1972 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook Volume II, 1942-1961 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook Volume III, 1945 (Box 6)
- Other Papers, 1963–1986; Series IV
  The Other Papers series includes ephemera collected by Rudolph Dunbar throughout his career.
  - ACER and Black Cultural archives, 1983–1986 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Ben Enwonwu "Dance Theme" Sculptures and Paintings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Printed materials (Box 7, Folder 66-72)
  - Programs, 1963–1977 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Who's Who in Music Directory, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 62)